This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
Let's
proceed on with
Poisson brackets.
Phase space has a structure to it.
It's not just a bunch of Ps and Qs, but
it's Ps and Qs with a certain kind of
structure. Spaces have structures. The
structures are the things which are
invariant under the various
transformations that you might want to
do.
Uh an example of the structure that can
be on a space, if you know anything
about curved spaces and differential
geometry and so forth, the metric
structure of certain of metrical spaces
of uh Riemann spaces
are part of the structure of those
spaces. They're characterized by a
metric on the space, a distance formula
between neighboring points.
Poisson structures are different than
metric structures. They're more
abstract.
And they were invented largely to
describe the structure of phase space
and its properties.
Its properties under transformations
which change the coordinates. Now, the
coordinates of a phase space are not
just the Qs.
The coordinates of a phase space are the
Qs and the Ps.
And roughly speaking, the question the
kind of question that you might ask is
what are the various transformations
that you can do? For example, it mix up
Ps and Qs
that preserve the basic structure of
classical mechanics.
As I said, this is the kind of question,
the kind of structural question, the
kind of formal question
that the French mathematicians were
awfully damn good at.
It turned out to be very important to
the future of physics.
It wasn't the French who figured out why
it was important. It was the French who
figured out how uh
how the basic structure of the French
and uh and Hamilton basically who
figured out what the structure of
classical mechanics is.
And uh
it got
more and more abstract.
The most concrete version was of course
Newton's version.
The most abstract version, I don't know
how abstract it can be. You probably can
get infinitely more abstract than
anything I'm likely to teach you.
But the most abstract end of it for our
purposes is the Poisson formulation of
uh of classical mechanics based on the
idea of Poisson brackets.
What Poisson brackets do
or what they what they're useful for is
describing flows on phase space.
One kind of flow on phase space is the
motion of the phase space with time or
the motion of the points in phase space
with time.
How the actual points evolve with time
under the influence of a particular
Hamiltonian.
That's one kind of flow on phase space.
But there are other kinds of flows on
phase space that you can imagine with
possibly somewhat different purposes.
For example,
we can talk about symmetries.
Now, we've talked about symmetries. The
basic symmetry that the problem for me
in explaining symmetries is not that
this is hard to explain, it's that there
aren't too many examples in classical
mechanics
that allow you a wide range of different
situations to describe. The basic
symmetries of of most classical
mechanical systems are rotations about
various axes and translations.
Uh special special uh systems
with particularly simple mathematics
sometimes have some hidden symmetries
that you might not have expected. But
the basic symmetries are just those, the
motions of space, translation, rotation.
As you move on to more advanced physics,
you discover more symmetries, different
kinds of symmetries, symmetries among
elementary particles and so forth. But
those are enough for for us now.
What do those symmetries have to do with
flows? Flows in phase space. Well, let
me begin with flows in just coordinate
space, X space.
We can think of a rotation. We can think
of rotations in space
as defining a kind of flow in the space.
Just imagine going from here
to here,
rotating our coordinates in space
by imagining an infinite number of
intermediate configurations.
And imagine in your head
going from one configuration to another
configuration of the axes of the axes of
the space continuously.
Or
we don't have to imagine motion of the
axes. We can actually imagine motion of
a system where we rotate the whole
system. We keep the axes fixed and
rotate the whole room.
That rotation might not have anything to
do with the actual time dependence of
the system. It simply allows us to
describe mathematically what a rotation
is. A rotation is something which is
built up out of lots of little
rotations, basically.
And so we can think of
the idea of a coordinate transformation
which rotates the coordinates of space
as a kind of flow.
Likewise, the translation of space, the
motion from one point, moving our
coordinate axes, not rotating them, but
translating them, we can also think of
that as being built up
a given translation as being built up by
a lot of little translations which
define a flow.
It's those flows in phase space, not
just in coordinate space, but
transformations which mix together or
potentially can mix together
both the Ps and the Qs into a richer
structure
than just the transformations which mix
up the coordinates. I use coordinates to
mean
Qs or Xs. I use phase space to talk
about the Ps and the Qs.
We can become interested and we will
become interested in transformations
which mix the Ps and Qs. And so it's a
richer family of transformations that we
can imagine.
And those flows which move things around
in phase space in various ways are
described
by the method of Poisson brackets.
So
uh
I try to make it a habit of not
beginning in the middle
even though I may have covered something
fairly completely in the previous
lecture.
So I like to go back over even
if it means I do it two or three times.
Let's just review what we know about
Poisson brackets.
Okay?
But let's let's be French
mathematicians. Let's abstract. Rather
than write down the concrete
the concrete definition of a Poisson
bracket, let's uh think about it from a
more abstract collection of postulates
or axioms about Poisson brackets.
The Poisson brackets
between what are what are what are
Poisson brackets uh what go into the
Poisson brackets? A thing I'll call A
and a thing that I'll call B.
Both A and B are imagined to be
functions of the Ps and Qs.
So we can write Poisson bracket of A
of P and Q
with B of P and Q.
First of all, has the abstract property
that it's anti-symmetric.
Anti-symmetric means that it changes
sign if you interchange A and B.
That's the first abstract property.
Oops, minus sign. Thank you.
Most important thing, the minus sign.
Right. So that's abstract property
number one. Abstract property number
two, I won't write down in detail unless
you ask me to.
It's the linearity.
Oh, let me write it down.
Supposing we have the Poisson bracket
of some combination of A and B.
Let's say alpha A, alpha and beta are
numbers, any numbers.
Alpha A plus beta B
Poisson bracket with C
is just equal to alpha
times the Poisson bracket of A with C
plus beta
times the Poisson bracket of B with C.
So that's the property of linearity.
This is anti-symmetry.
This is linearity.
Then there's the product rule.
What kinds of things are the As and the
Bs?
Capital A, what kind of what? Things are
they? Functions. Functions of Ps and Qs.
P squared plus Q squared, sine of P,
whatever. It's real valued. Not
necessarily.
But you can add
There's no reason why in these formulas
you can't take alpha and beta to be
complex numbers.
But you can't add As and Bs. That's all
I'm saying. You can add A Oh, yes, you
can add As and Bs, absolutely. You can
add As and Bs. They're just adding the
functions. Yeah.
You can certainly add A's and B's.
They're just functions.
Uh
in classical mechanics, there isn't much
reason to be thinking about complex
valued functions, but there's no reason
that you can't. And sometimes you do.
Sometimes you do. Sometimes it's useful.
So,
they're just general functions of the
coordinates and momenta. Remember the
coordinates, when I write down P's and
Q's, I don't just mean one P and one Q.
I mean N P's and N Q's, where N is the
number of coordinates of the system.
Okay, so that's the linearity.
Then there's the product rule.
The Poisson bracket of A * B
with C
is equal
to A
* the Poisson bracket of B with C.
Plus
B
No.
A. Thank you.
B.
Now, I've written these formulas in a
particular order here.
I've left the A on the left here and the
B on the right. There's no reason for
that. These are just numbers. That is to
say, they're functions whose values are
just numbers,
and it doesn't matter whether you
multiply A
* the Poisson bracket or the Poisson
bracket * A.
Mathematically speaking, these things
all commute, which means you can
multiply them in any order.
I've written it in a form
which won't mean anything to you now,
but it will mean next quarter when we
study quantum mechanics. In quantum
mechanics, things don't commute, and
I've written in a particular order,
which is still correct in quantum
mechanics. But, for our purposes now,
A * the Poisson bracket of B and C is
just nothing but Poisson bracket of B
and C * A. So, it doesn't matter whether
the B's come first or or the Poisson
brackets come first. It does matter the
order that you write down the Poisson
bracket itself.
That order does matter because you have
to change the sign if you were to change
them. Yeah. So, these So, these A's and
B's are actually scalars? They're scalar
functions. Uh
scalar has to do with their properties
under rotation of space, and so I mean,
it's not a vector.
They could be components of vectors.
Vectors meaning
Uh oh. Oh. Oh. We're not talking about
matrix multiplication, if that's what
you mean. We're not talking about
vector. We're talking about just
numerical multiplication. Yeah.
Let's not call them scalars.
Let's call them numbers.
Let's call them numbers. Numbers which
uh which simply mean that when you
multiply two numbers, it doesn't matter
which order you multiply them.
Yeah, mathematicians tend to just use
the word scalar. Oh, do they? Yeah.
Well, physicists use the word scalar to
represent the the property of a system
under rotation. They are P and Q. The
alpha and beta are scalars.
But, they you know, they're just
functions.
Cuz they depend on the We're going to
get into linguistic ambiguities here
because because it may be that
mathematicians use the terminology
different than physicists.
Physicist means by a scalar
something which doesn't transform under
rotation of space.
Okay?
Uh mathematicians may use the word
scalar to mean a number.
Physicists often use the word C number,
meaning a constant number that doesn't
matter whether it's constant or not.
There There's a whole terminology here
that we'll get confused about. But, the
important The important thing is we're
talking about multiplications which are
commutative.
But, the Poisson bracket process itself
is not commutative.
Uh
A * B A Poisson bracket with B is not B
Poisson bracket with A.
Okay, I think we know what we mean.
Those are the basic abstract rules.
And then there's some concrete rules. If
the functions A and B are simply P's and
Q's and nothing but P's and Q's,
then we presume that there are some
simple laws of Poisson brackets or
simple rules for Poisson brackets for
P's with Q's, P's with P's, and Q's with
Q's.
Uh if we only had one P and one Q,
then we could immediately write down
that P with P
with now means Poisson bracket with. I
get tired of saying take the Poisson
bracket with. With simply means take the
Poisson bracket.
P with P
can only be equal to zero.
That follows from the antisymmetry.
P with P is equal to minus P with P from
the top equation, if we interchange the
order. But, if something is equal to its
own negative, it's got to be equal to
zero.
Same is true with Q.
Hm?
What's that?
Right.
But, that doesn't tell you what the
Poisson bracket of P with Q is.
Let's take Q with P.
For that, we need to use the definition
of of the Poisson bracket.
The definition in terms of derivatives,
and then we just find out that it's
equal to one.
Yeah. Now, if we put if we put
subscripts in,
we can't be quite as confident that this
is true for every I and J.
Nevertheless, by the definition of
Poisson brackets in terms of
derivatives,
remember that every Poisson bracket has
in it derivatives with respect to P and
derivatives with respect to Q.
Well, you can't differentiate a P with
respect to Q. You get zero.
So, anytime you take a Poisson bracket
of a P with a P, you must get zero. A Q
with a Q, you must get zero.
But, a Q with a P,
you get one
or zero, depending on whether I is equal
to J.
Delta I J. Delta I J is the Kronecker
symbol.
Kronecker. Kronecker.
I don't know if I spelled that right or
not.
No, see here?
I don't know.
Yeah. It's either zero or one, depending
on whether I is equal to J or not.
Namely, it's equal to one if I is equal
to J and zero otherwise.
That's the Kronecker delta symbol.
And that's the uh these are the Poisson
bracket relations for P and Q.
Now, it's easy to prove
that if you take
Well, in fact, you can prove You can
prove almost everything about Poisson
brackets just from these relationships.
But, if you also allow yourself to use
uh the definition of the Poisson
bracket, which can be derived
incidentally from these relations,
um
but if you use that, you can also
immediately prove
that the Poisson bracket of any function
of the Q's, not the P's,
with any other function of the Q's,
in other words, if both functions only
have Q in them, that's automatically
zero.
Why? Because again, every Poisson
bracket will have derivatives with
respect to P and derivatives with
respect to Q in its definition, so at
least
So, it will turn out to be zero if
there's nothing to differentiate with
respect to P, so to speak.
All right? So, this will be zero.
Likewise, any function of P
with any other function of P
will also be equal to zero.
It's only when you take Poisson brackets
between functions of P and with
functions
in which at least one of them has both P
and Q in it. No, that's not right.
What do we have to say?
Uh something
on one side has to mismatch something on
the other side. There's got to be a P on
one side and a Q on the other side to
get anything nonzero.
Okay.
So,
that's a collection of rules.
There There are more rules, but they all
follow from these. There's no
independent rules. For example,
supposing we take the Poisson bracket of
any function of Q
with P.
Poisson bracket of any function of Q
What is that equal to?
Well, I'll tell you right now what it's
equal to, and then we'll try to prove
it.
That is equal to the derivative of F
with respect to Q.
So, taking a Poisson bracket with P
is the same as differentiating with
respect to Q.
We can see that in a number of ways.
One way of seeing it is just use the
definition, but another way of seeing it
this here we can prove it by
mathematical induction.
Let's prove it for all polynomials f of
q. If we prove something like this for
every conceivable polynomial it'll be
true for every function. Every function
can be arbitrarily well approximated by
a sufficiently complicated polynomial.
The linearity would tell us we need to
only prove it for monomials.
So let's prove it for some monomials.
Let's take one. Let's take f of q equals
one.
What does this equation say for f of q
equals one? It says the Poisson bracket
of one. One is a function. It's a
perfectly good function. It doesn't vary
but it but it is a function.
One with p
must be equal to the derivative of one
with respect to q. What is the
derivative of one with respect to q?
Zero.
Now
how do I prove this?
I'll tell you how I can prove it.
Mhm?
Yeah yeah yeah. Yeah but I didn't prove
these but let let me give you a simple
proof of this one.
The simple proof of this one is to use
the product formula.
One squared with p
is equal to one
with one p
plus
one p
with one
which is equal to twice
Poisson bracket of one with p.
But one squared is just one. So this
says that the Poisson bracket of one
with p is twice the Poisson bracket of
one with p.
That proves it's zero.
Okay. So indeed the first one is right.
Let's go
to the next monomial.
Q with p.
That's the next more complicated
monomial for f.
Q with p should be equal to the
derivative of q with respect to q which
is just equal to one.
But that's certainly true. That is the
defining property
of
q with p.
Let's just go one more. Q squared with
p.
Q squared with p
for that we use the product formula
again and that gives us
q with qp.
Plus
qp
with q.
Poisson bracket of q with p is just one.
So this just gives us two q.
And that happens to be the derivative of
q squared with respect to q.
All right. So by a process of course we
use mathematical induction
to prove it for q to the nth.
Once you prove it for q to the nth
then you use linearity to prove it for
every polynomial.
And then to go from polynomials to
arbitrary differentiable smooth
functions you can use the fact that any
smooth function can be approximated
arbitrarily well by a polynomial.
So in fact
we see that
Poisson bracketing with p
is simply another way to differentiate.
Likewise
differentiating with respect to p
is the same as taking the Poisson
bracket
with q.
Notice there's a slight difference in
the order of Poisson brackets here. To
differentiate with respect to q
you take the Poisson bracket with p with
p on the right hand side. To
differentiate with respect to p
you um
you put the q first.
All right. So that's another
property.
Yeah.
Assuming everything is continuous
functions uh
every function is continuous
differentiable multiply differentiable.
Um
I'm assuming that. Yeah.
All right. So we have our You but one
could say we have an algebra of Poisson
brackets
that characterize the relationships
between p's and q's in the phase space.
Now we add to that
another postulate about the time
evolution of a system.
And that postulate again can be derived
It can be completely derived from
Hamilton's equations. We've derived it.
We've derived it at least twice as I
remember.
But let's just write it down. It can be
just added to these postulates as one
more postulate.
And it is that the time derivative a dot
of any function of p and q
Let's just remember what that means. We
have the phase space
which is
coordinateized by p's and q's.
We have points of phase space moving
through the phase space under the
equations of motion of the system.
And as they move through the phase space
the value
of a of p and q will change along the
orbit of the phase point.
All right.
That's what a dot means. The rate of
change of a of p and q because you're
moving along the orbit in phase space
that time derivative
is the Poisson bracket
of a
with h.
This basically sets the pattern
that a flow
a flow applied to a function
We have a function on the phase space
and we apply the flow to it. I don't
know. We apply the flow to it.
That causes the function to change as we
move along the flow.
That flow
is characterized as a Poisson bracket
with something. That something happens
to be the Hamiltonian if we're talking
about the genuine flow with time.
Okay. In other words the real flow of
the system as time evolves. But we may
just be interested in some mathematical
flow that has nothing to do with the
time evolution but just has to do with
the fact for example that we're studying
some symmetry which might correspond to
to a change of coordinates.
Uh through a sequence of intermediate uh
Hamiltonian happens to be p squared over
2m.
And we apply
we apply this to
p dot.
It tells us that p dot time derivative
of p is the Poisson bracket of p with p
squared over 2m.
Well that's zero because of a formula
which I think I have erased which says
that the Poisson bracket of any function
of p with any other function of p is
zero.
Okay. So that's zero. That tells us
momentum conservation. On the other hand
q dot
is q with p.
Now we use the product formula. We use
the product formula. We have p squared
here and q here.
The product formula can be used to tell
us
that this
that this is just p over m.
We have p squared over 2m. That gives us
a p with a q is one. Well you know how
to do this.
Just gives us a p over m without ever
using uh
anything other than the algebra of these
functions the algebra of these Poisson
brackets
we can conclude that the Poisson bracket
of q with p squared over 2m is p over m.
And that tells us that q dot Excuse me.
The q dot is p over m.
And that of course is the uh
the velocity as a function of momentum
for a non-relativistic particle with
Hamiltonian p squared over 2m.
All right. So without knowing
Hamilton's equations we could derive the
equations Hamilton's equations from the
algebra of these Poisson brackets.
Okay, now let's come to
a wider class of transformations. Yes.
Just a little tangent on that. You said
non-relativistic. Does this actually
hold up in relativity? Mhm.
Mhm.
Yep.
But it's it's a little more complicated.
Yes, it does.
These basic formulas
hold
for every physical system that I know
of.
I don't know of any physical system
where these basic formulas don't hold,
including general relativity, including
quantum field theory. Well,
I in the in the appropriate form in
quantum mechanical appropriate form in
quantum mechanics they hold, but for all
classical situation
all classical systems these formulas
absolutely hold. Quantum field Sorry,
field theory, electromagnetism,
everything.
Okay.
Now let's move on to symmetries.
What are symmetries? Symmetries are
coordinate are transformations.
Transformations of a system
which don't change the dynamics.
Now, in the cases we've studied up till
now, symmetries would typically of the
form
changes of the variables
Q.
Without mixing in the P's. For example,
rotations of space
mix up the X's and the Y's. They don't
mix in the momenta
with the X's and Y's.
Could there be more interesting
symmetries of nature which do mix the
P's and Q's?
And if they do, what are the rules and
what are the laws
which allow you to mix up P's and Q's
and preserve the structure of classical
mechanics?
That's the question. What are the
allowable
transformations
that don't screw up mechanics so badly
that it becomes
unrecognizable?
Recognizable means that it has the
Poisson form.
All right, so that's the question
question we want to ask. What are the
allowable transformations on phase
space?
Allowable transformations mean they
don't ruin this Poisson structure that
we've written down.
If you were just to take a bunch of P's
and Q's which satisfy this algebra of
Poisson brackets and make arbitrary
transformations,
let's let's do it this way. Let's
Let's suppose we have a single P and a
single Q.
Now, let me make a transformation.
I'm going to make a new transformation
to new P's and Q's, capital P, which is
going to be twice little P
and capital Q
which is twice little Q.
Does this preserve the Poisson bracket
structure?
It does not. Let me show you why.
Let's calculate the Poisson bracket
of big P with big Q.
Well, that's easy. I don't even have to
do any work here. I just know that this
is the Poisson bracket of twice little P
with twice little Q. What's that?
Four.
It's the wrong answer. It does not
preserve the form of the Poisson bracket
relations.
Let me try something else. Instead of
big P equals twice little P, let's take
it to be 1/2 little P.
Now what happens?
What's the Poisson bracket of big P with
with big Q?
One.
This formula
has preserved the structure of Poisson
brackets.
If I do this transformation on the P's
and Q's, it's not necessarily a symmetry
of a physical system,
but it is another set of coordinates
which has exactly the same Poisson
bracket relations as the original P's
and Q's.
Kind of interesting. What I've done on
to the phase space
is
I have squeezed it in one direction by a
factor of two and stretched it in the
other direction by a factor of two. And
that has preserved the structure of the
uh of the Poisson bracket relations.
Stretching both directions by a factor
of two did not uh preserve the
relations.
How about the following?
Supposing I Let's Let's try another
example.
Let's take
ca two in the
resulting it seems like conservation of
volume or mass. It's basically
conservation of area. Area, yeah.
Yeah.
Uh but it's conservation it's
it's a little more complicated. It Once
you leave the domain of just one P and
one Q, it's more complicated. But for
one P and one Q,
the
uh the transformations that we're
talking about are the ones that preserve
areas.
For more P's and more Q's it's more
complicated.
But let's just do one or one or two more
examples.
Um
let's take uh
big P is Let's rotate P into Q.
Rotate P into Q. In other words, we have
the PQ axes
and we rotate.
Let's take big P equals cosine theta
little P
plus sine theta
little Q.
And let's take big Q
equal
minus sine of theta
little P
plus cosine theta
little Q.
This is the form of a rotation in phase
space.
It's a rotation in phase space where
you've rotated the axes.
From what I just told you about areas,
it's quite clear that this also should
preserve the structure of Poisson
brackets. Let's check it.
Let's calculate the Poisson bracket of
big P with big Q. Do I have to check the
Poisson bracket of big P with big P
big P with big P?
This is linguistically the hardest
lecture for me.
Do I have to check the Poisson bracket
of big P with too many B's and P's. Big
P with big P.
What's that?
By the linearity it all works.
It all just comes right. Well, well,
let's just say big P with big P.
Antisymmetry tells me it's zero. Big P
with big P has to be the same as big P
with big P in the opposite order.
That tells me it's zero. Antisymmetry
tells me big P with big P is zero. It
tells me big Q with big Q is zero. It's
only big P with big Q that I got to
watch out for.
Okay, so let's just do it.
So that's going to be
uh
Let's big
big Q with big P
equals
cosine
Sorry, sine uh
sine theta
Ah, let's let's begin with Q's. All
right.
Um
cosine theta Q
plus sine theta P.
That's this one here.
This one of them minus one of them is
minus, right?
This one is minus.
And then the other one is cosine theta P
plus sine theta Q.
All right, the only combinations which
give me anything are a Q with a P and a
P with a Q.
All right, let's first take the Q with
the P over here. That's going to have
cosine squared theta in front of it.
Cosine squared theta
Poisson bracket of Q with P. Poisson
bracket of Q with P is one.
And then we're going to have minus
sine squared theta.
That's coming from here. But what's the
Poisson bracket of P with Q?
Minus one. So that corrects this sign
here and makes it plus sine squared
and gives us a one again.
All right, so the rotation of
coordinates
preserve the Poisson bracket structure.
The stretching of one coordinate and the
squeezing of the other coordinate by the
same factor, it didn't have to be two
incidentally,
that will preserve the Poisson bracket
structure.
On the other hand, other kinds of
transformations will not preserve it. In
particular, those that don't preserve
the area.
So there are those which do and those
which don't.
Those transformations which preserve the
entire class of them and they can be
much more complicated than this.
In general, for arbitrary numbers of P's
and Q's, the transformations which
preserve the Poisson bracket structure
are called canonical transformations.
Canonical.
Canonical
are those which keep intact
the relations between the the Poisson
bracket relations between P's and Q's.
If they keep the relation between P's
and Q's, then they will keep all the
Poisson bracket relations between P
square, Q square, P uh whatever you
have.
What?
What's that?
The equation of motion should be
unchanged.
Yeah, but you have to remember that when
you change the that the Hamiltonian has
to be expressed in terms of the new
variables. Yes, that's correct.
That's right.
These are not
These are not gauge transformations.
Uh no, these are canonical
transformations. They're not gauge
transformations.
They're not redundancies of a
description, they're just changes of a
description
to new coordinates.
Um The gauge transformations are adding
something on
to the existing coordinates of fields.
Transforming the coordinates themselves
in the relation.
Well, those are not called gauge
transformations. Uh
Gauge transformations have a definite
meaning.
In this system, how do you know that P
and Q are canonical?
Uh the point is if you start with
canonical P's and Q's
and you do canonical transformations on
them,
they they stay canonical. Now, that's a
tautology.
But to make it not a
tautology, what do you mean by
canonical? You mean these Poisson
bracket relations.
These are the canonical Poisson bracket
relations.
If after transformation
all of the Poisson bracket relations are
kept intact, then it's called a
canonical transformation.
Okay.
I have Okay, I have a
general question about
um
must it preserve
the Poisson bracket to be a canonical
transformation?
Mhm.
As opposed to
um
I guess Well, let's let's say
if you have any two sets of P's and
you know, small P's and small Q's and
big P's and big
With big P's and big Q's being functions
of the small P's and small Q's.
Okay. They're changes of coordinates is
what they are. They're changes of P Q
coordinates.
might have two different sets of
coordinates
of different systems. No, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no. We're talking about
different coordinates for the same
system.
That's what we're talking about.
Different coordinates for the same
system.
And by coordinates I now mean
coordinates on phase space.
So, we're talking about different
representations of the same system by
different choices
of axes or different choices of
coordinates on the same phase space.
So, you can't go from arbitrarily
one phase space to any other
No, no, no, no, no. We're talking about
the same system.
Yeah, these are changes of description
rather than changes of system.
Okay. Changes of of description of a
given system.
Right, we must keep that in mind.
It doesn't mean anything, for example,
to
to change the coordinates of from a
harmonic oscillator to a system of 10 10
to the 23rd molecules. It doesn't mean
anything. It won't necessarily be a
canonical transformation that could
transform one
totally different system to another. It
doesn't
It doesn't mean anything. I mean, if it
if it does mean something, we have to
make up a definition for what it means.
Here, we're we're talking about P's and
Q's which are really functions of the
original P's and Q's, which means
they're just re-descriptions of the same
system.
Yeah. But aren't they just characterized
by dimensionality? I mean
If n is 5, then there's a set of there's
a whole set of canonical transformations
for 5 P's and 5 Q's.
Mhm.
Yeah.
The the phase space of n of n degrees of
freedom are all isomorphic to each
other.
But still, you don't you don't um
Nevertheless, when you're talking about
canonical transformations, you're
talking about the changes of description
of a given system.
Uh
Yeah, but the
different phase spaces all with the same
number of degrees of freedom are
isomorphic to each other.
And that's correct.
Yeah.
But still, you don't transform between
systems.
Right.
All right, now we want to come to what
is the heart of the discussion, this
subject of symmetries itself.
Mhm.
Is there any way of expressing
the necessary and sufficient conditions
for something to be a canonical
transformation other than the way you
put it?
Um
This is the necessary and sufficient
condition.
Uh that the P's and Q's uh preserve
their commit their uh their Poisson
bracket structure. That is the
necessary. Now, you're asking
you're asking if you give me a certain
Well, what are you asking? I guess
there's another way of expressing it in
some way other than
you know, that's Poisson
general expression. Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, there is another way of expressing
it that is of great general interest,
but is also not completely general.
We build we tend to build
transformations, not all of them, but we
tend to build transformations out of
infinitesimal transformations,
out of small steps.
Okay.
If we're talking about an infinitesimal
transformation,
I'll explain exactly what I mean by an
infinitesimal transformation in a
moment, but I think you you know what I
mean though. Yeah.
Yeah. If we're talking about
infinitesimal transformations, then yes,
there is a way to describe them,
a unique special way to describe them,
which is which we're about to come to
now.
So, if we can build up the
transformations
out of infinitesimal transformations,
and what is an infinitesimal
transformation? It means one
Well, let's just write down what it
means.
It means Q
is almost exactly equal to little Q,
but with a very small
deviation, and that small deviation
we'll just call delta sub Q, delta of Q,
and this of course is a function of the
Q's and the P's.
It just means the deviation
from a trivial transformation, big Q
equals little Q,
is infinitesimal.
In practice, what it means is in the
formulas, we will drop things
proportional to quadratic and higher
powers of the deltas.
It means that small quantities mean
quantities which are so small that we
can drop higher powers in them.
That's what we'll always mean by an
infinitesimal operation, that we can
drop higher powers. Now, we can always
build transformations out of sequences
of little transformations, for each one
of which
we can drop higher powers, but then we
have to combine them together, and
sometimes that makes something more
complicated.
But we can test out very easily what are
the rules for infinitesimal
canonical transformations.
I won't bother writing down that it's a
function of P and Q.
All right.
Uh let's just remember that the deltas
are themselves functions. They're
functions, but they're small
such that we can ignore higher powers of
them.
All right, let's first write down the
condition
that this be a canonical transformation.
Incidentally, of course, there are some
indices here.
I'll suppress the indices up until the
last step.
Let's write down the condition that this
be a canonical transformation.
All right. It just says
that
All right, let's let's just do it for
let's just do it as if it was just one P
and one Q.
And we can fill in the gaps later.
Okay. Um
Poisson bracket of big P with big Q.
That's the interesting one here.
Big P with big Q. That's just going to
be the Poisson bracket of little Q
with little P. We'll stick in the I's
later.
Plus
the Poisson bracket of delta Q
with little P
plus the Poisson bracket
of Q
with delta P.
I've just stuck in for big Q Q plus
delta Q, for big P P plus delta P and
there's and then use linearity to expand
it out. I've left out one term. I've
left out the Poisson bracket of delta Q
with delta P but that's already
quadratic in small quantities.
Quadratic in small quantities are too
small to be significant.
So, this is our formula.
Now, what do we want to be true? We want
this to be equal to this.
So, a necessary and sufficient condition
then is that delta Q
with P
should be equal to minus
Q
with delta P.
Let me show you how to satisfy that.
Uh this actually is necessary and
sufficient
but uh
it's it's not hard to show that it's
necessary and sufficient but let me just
show you the construction.
What do we do?
We write that delta Q
is equal to some small number.
This this the epsilon is just a small
number in the problem.
Delta Q, delta P are all proportional to
the same small number. I introduced
explicitly the uh the small number so
that I'll know uh so that I keep track
of it.
times
the Poisson bracket of Q with something.
With what? With an object that's called
the generator of the canonical
transformation.
G of P and Q.
And
delta P
is equal to epsilon
times P
with G.
Another way to say it is that every
cana- every infinitesimal canonical
transformation
is characterized by a function G of P
and Q
which itself defines a flow. Is it the
same or reverse in order?
Same order.
All right.
This is a kind of flow, a coordinate
transformation in particular an
infinitesimal coordinate transformation
is a kind of flow on the phase space.
You take every point and you shift it a
little bit. You take every point and you
shift it a little bit.
That's a flow on the phase space. And
flows on the phase space are
characterized by things called
generators. Generators are functions of
P and Q and they characterize how the
flow takes place.
Let me prove now the theorem.
I'm going to prove the theorem that says
that if delta Q and delta P are obtained
by Poisson brackets with a generator
then this will always be true.
It goes the other way also.
All right. This is uh this is not hard
to prove.
First of all, what is the Poisson
bracket of Q with G of P and Q?
Remember, taking a Poisson bracket with
Q
is the same as differentiating with
respect to P.
What is this? This is dQ by dQ dG by dP
minus Yeah, this is just epsilon
dG
by dP.
Just using the definition of Poisson
bracket now.
dQ by dQ dG by dP that just gives you dG
by dP
and then dQ by dP uh that's zero.
What about this one?
This one is equal to minus epsilon
dG by dQ.
So, now we have specific
formulas for delta P and delta Q. Here
they are.
Let's plug them into this formula over
here.
What's delta Q? Delta Q is epsilon dG by
dP. Epsilon
Poisson bracket of dG by dP
with P
and that should equal minus
Poisson bracket of Q
with delta P. What's What's delta P
again?
Delta P is
minus
dG by dQ, right?
Epsilon.
All right. The minus signs cancel
themselves out.
I hope.
And what is the Poisson bracket with P?
It just differentiates with respect to
Q.
So, this is just the second derivative
of G with respect to P and Q.
What's Poisson bracket with Q?
Derivative with respect to P.
This is identically the left side and
the right side are identically equal to
each other.
Okay. They're identically equal to each
other each one being the second
derivative of G with respect to P and Q.
Okay.
So
Okay. So, here's what we find. We find
that flows which are generated by
Poisson bracketing with respect to a
generator
always define canonical transformations.
A special case of this is the
Hamiltonian flow.
Let's look at this equation here. What
does it say?
Supposing we were talking about the time
motion of a system, the time motion of a
system is Q dot
equals Poisson bracket of Q with H.
Well, if I write that Q dot is delta Q
by delta T
and I just think of delta T as a small
epsilon.
Let's put epsilon here.
In other words, I change the time
interval by amount epsilon
then the Hamiltonian flow is exactly the
same as the sort of thing I've written
here.
Hamiltonian evolution of a system is a
canonical transformation.
In other words, the coordinate
transformations of Ps and Qs which are
generated by the actual flow of the
system
is itself a special case of a canonical
transformation.
Furthermore, all canonical
transformations can be generated by
picking some generator as if it were the
Hamiltonian imagining in our mind a
Hamiltonian which caused a flow
which took the points from one to
another.
That defines the most general class of
of canonical transformations.
Now
Yeah, the most general I
I think I'm saying something a little
too strong. Uh I'm not sure. Maybe I'm
not. Um
Every canonical transformation that I
know Now I know I'm saying something
correct. Every canonical transformation
that I know of
I think it's true. Can be generated from
infinitesimal canonical transformations.
If it can be generated from If it can be
generated from an infinitesimal
canonical transformation
then it's got a generator G of P and Q
which
which allows it to be constructed in
this way. So, if you want a small
canonical transformation which just
displaces the points a little bit
you just take Poisson brackets of the
variables you're interested in with the
generator and that gives you the changes
in the in the in the phase space
coordinates.
That's the basic idea.
That all motions on the phase space
whether they have to do with the actual
time evolution or whether they just have
to do with coordinate transformations
moving points around
are of the form of canonical
transformations generated by generators.
The Hamiltonian being a special case.
Yeah. Are there any restrictions on what
the Hamiltonian
can be? Is it It looks like G is just
of another system. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
It is.
It's just a
It could be the Hamiltonian for another
system.
And the Hamiltonian could just be some
arbitrarily arbitrary flow.
Uh that's right.
What the Hamiltonian is of course is
really determined by the physics of a
system, experiment and all that kind of
thing.
But the mathematics cannot tell you
whether G is the Hamiltonian or H is the
Hamiltonian. You do an experiment to
find out.
Okay. Now we can
Now we can um
discuss
if the transformations which we are
allowed to do which preserve the
structure of mechanics are canonical.
Then what is the subclass of those for a
given system with a given Hamiltonian?
What is the subclass that are called
symmetries?
Symmetries are the canonical
transformations which don't change the
Hamiltonian.
Just like in the case of Lagrangians,
we said that the symmetries were the
coordinate transformations which didn't
change the Lagrangian.
Now the more general idea becomes
coordinate transformations in phase
space which are canonical and which
don't change the energy.
Those are the symmetries of a mechanical
system.
We can actually say that in a more in a
somewhat geometric way.
Here's our phase space.
Oh, incidentally, I didn't keep track of
the little indices I. You can go home
and do the derivation over again keeping
track of all the indices I and J
and see that the construction still
works.
It's It's more or less obvious.
Okay.
But let's imagine here's our phase
space, multi-dimensional phase space.
Now the Hamiltonian corresponds to some
flow.
And it's also a canonical
transformation.
The infinitesimal small time flow from
one point to another is the canonical
trans is the is generated by the
Hamiltonian
and the full transformation over a
period of time is canonical.
Now let's imagine that some other
quantity
a generator G
that generates another flow. It's not to
be thought of as the time the the time
evolution of the system. It's just
another flow on the phase space.
Just another motion on the phase space
which moves points through the phase
space in some other way.
In general, you can see from this
picture
that
uh the new flow, the green flow, will
change the value of the energy along the
flow.
But supposing it's true supposing it's
true that the green flow
G
and the black flow H, the Hamiltonian of
the system, are in just such a way
that the flow
along the G direction doesn't change the
energy. Causes the energy not to change
at all. In other words, flows the system
along surfaces of constant energy.
Then it's called a symmetry.
It's a symmetry. G is a symmetry
if the flow created by G doesn't change
the energy.
What's the condition for that?
This is easy.
Mhm?
Right. Right. Geometrically the
condition but in a multi-dimensional
space it's not so obvious.
All right.
Um
Here's how Q and P change under the
flow.
Let's take a general function of P and
Q.
Let's take a general function of P and Q
and see how it changes along this flow.
I'm not going to call I'm going to call
a function A again. Let's call it A.
How does A change along the flow?
Well,
it changes dA by dP
times delta P
plus dA by dQ
delta Q.
But what is delta P and delta Q? Here we
have them. They're proportional to dG
but
dG by dP and dG by dQ.
So this is let's see delta P is
dG by dQ
dG by dP.
In other words, not too surprisingly
the change in any function of A is just
proportional
Is an epsilon in here, isn't there?
Is just epsilon
times the Poisson bracket
of A with G.
This is exactly the same formula we used
for time derivatives of things when G
was the Hamiltonian.
The change of functions along the
Hamiltonian flow is just a Poisson
bracket with the Hamiltonian. The change
of an arbitrary function along any flow
is just a Poisson bracket with the
generator of the flow.
That's what these generators do.
Poisson brackets with the generators
create the flow and they give you the
derivatives or the way the functions
change along the flow.
All right. So then, what does it say
that the energy does not change along
the flow G?
It says that the Poisson bracket
of H
with G
is equal to zero.
It says that H does not change along the
flow G.
Right?
If I were to just plug in here for A H
everywheres
this would just be the Poisson bracket
of H with G.
So this is the condition that the energy
doesn't change along the symmetry flow
G.
But now we can read this the other way
also. This also tells us
that G with H is equal to zero.
H with G and G with H are just the
negative of each other. And what does
this equation say?
This says that the time derivative of G
vanishes.
Right?
Remember the other equation was that A
with H
equals A dot.
The same equation which says that H
doesn't vary along the along the flow G
says that G doesn't flow vary along the
flow H.
But what does this equation say?
It says that A is conserved.
Right? It says that A is conserved.
So if you have a Hamiltonian
and you have a generator G
a quantity a quantity G
which has the property
that the flows created by G don't change
the energy,
then the flows created by the energy,
that's the time dependence of the
system, don't change
G.
This is kind of the reciprocal relation
is interesting reciprocal relationship.
If you have two quantities H and G
and you say H is the Hamiltonian which
generates the time dependence
and G doesn't change the Hamiltonian,
then if you switch the system and you
said G was the Hamiltonian
and H was just some arbitrary thing
I think you get the point. I'm going to
I'm going to use too many words to say
it. There's a parallel relationship
between quantities which are conserved
and the energy of a system.
Parallel symmetrical relationship
between them.
Um I think this would be a good point to
stop.
This is a very very highly abstract
business
and um
it does have to do with the intrinsic
structure of classical mechanics, but as
I said to you time and again
the place where the real glory of this
comes forth is in quantum mechanics.
It's very abstract in classical
mechanics. It's extremely concrete in in
quantum mechanics. Much easier to
understand in quantum mechanics. What
could be an example?
Of what? In quantum mechanics.
Angular momentum and energy.
Uh H could be let's see. H could be the
energy of a system. It could be P
squared over 2M.
Uh plus uh
I don't know. Function of function of X
squared plus Y squared, let's say.
That could be H. G could be the angular
momentum.
Angular momentum is XPY minus YPX.
If you calculate the Poisson bracket
between this and this, you find that
it's zero corresponding to Let's do
that. Oh, yeah. Yeah, it's going to be
complicated.
Um
Let's do it for a free particle.
It's going to be a little too
complicated to do in general.
Yeah, let's do it for a free particle.
Okay, so let's take P squared over 2M.
And that means Px squared plus Py
squared.
Do you mind if I
set M equal to 1?
No. Px squared over 2 plus Py squared
over 2.
That's the Hamiltonian.
G is the angular momentum.
The expression for the This is two
dimensions just for simplicity, two
dimensions. G is the angular momentum.
That's
XPY
- YPX
Okay, now we want to start calculating
Poisson brackets between G and H. This
is not too bad.
Remember all P's
Hm?
No, this isn't P's.
Right.
Yeah.
X's and Y's are are Q's.
Good.
All right.
It wouldn't be true if I just took XPY
or YPX, but it's a combination XPY -
Okay, so let's do it.
Poisson bracket of G with H.
Okay, so what is that?
It's going to have XPY with PX and it's
going to have XPY with PY. How about
let's do XPY with PY first of all?
Do I get anything from that?
The Poisson bracket of an X with a PY is
zero.
Remember, the only non-zero Poisson
brackets that you begin with are X with
PX and Y with PY.
When I start calculating XPY with PY,
I'm not going to get anything.
PY Poisson bracket with PY is zero, X
with PY is zero.
So, there's nothing on this side which
has a non-zero Poisson bracket with
anything over here.
The only non-zero Poisson brackets are X
with PX and Y with PY.
Okay, so let's begin with X with PX.
Let's This is going to be then
Poisson bracket of XPY
with PX squared over two.
And then the other term will be minus
YPX
with PY squared over two with PY squared
over two.
Okay, how about XPY with PX squared over
two?
Well, we use the product formula here.
We take out one term is just PY
with XPX squared over two.
Then there's another term where the X
comes out
and PY gets Poisson'd with PX. But
what's Poisson of X PY with PX?
Zero.
So, this is the only term coming from
the first bracket.
PY
times X with PX squared. What's X with
PX squared?
Remember what Poisson bracketing with a
Q does.
It differentiates.
So, X with PX squared gives what?
Just PX. This whole thing is just PYPX.
It's just PYPX. What about this one?
We'll get a PX on the outside and we'll
get Y with PY squared, which will be
PY. Which will just be minus PYPX.
So,
this is an example of two generators
which
have zero
keep wanting to use the word commute. In
quantum mechanics, it would be commute.
But let's not use that terminology. This
is an example of two quantities, two
generators, which have vanishing Poisson
bracket between them.
The implication is the following. If the
Hamiltonian is PX squared plus PY
squared,
then the angular momentum is conserved.
If we invented a new system where the
Hamiltonian happens to be this thing,
crazy Hamiltonian, but let's do it
anyway. A new system where the
Hamiltonian is this thing,
then this object would be conserved.
The Poisson bracket between them is
zero, so whichever one is the
Hamiltonian, the other one is conserved.
And again, the idea that the Hamiltonian
doesn't change
under a transformation, that is the
basic idea of a symmetry.
That a symmetry is an operation which
doesn't change the energy.
But we see here there's a rich structure
to the whole thing, a much richer
structure than
um
than
well, than you might have expected.
Okay, any any questions about this? And
then I want to move on to uh
I want to move back and
review what we said the first time.
Yeah.
What did you say? Yeah. Oh.
Let's see what it means. Let's see what
it means.
To see what it means, it means it simply
means let's find out the equations of
motion that go with it and ask how a
particle would move under the influence
of that Hamiltonian.
I don't know. Let's see. I never worked
it out.
Here's a Hamiltonian, new system.
Hamiltonian is XPY - YPX.
Let's work out Hamilton's equations.
Hamilton's equations
say
uh X dot
is equal to the Poisson bracket of X
with H.
What's the Poisson bracket of X with H?
Can anybody read this off?
Where does it come from? Which term?
The only term in H which can contribute
to a Poisson bracket with X is a term
that has PX in it.
So,
this is looks like it's going to be
minus Y.
X dot equals minus Y.
And what about Y dot?
Y dot is equal to X.
Anybody have any idea what kind of
motion this is?
Circle. Circular motion.
It just describes something going in a
circle.
Yeah, I've I've meant to change now. I
said let's make up a new system
where the Hamiltonian just happens to be
XPY - YPX.
And what do I get?
I get
a system which just moves in a circle
counter-clockwise direction like so.
So, if we had some mechanical system
which could only move in a circle, we
would describe it by this Hamiltonian,
but then we would find that PX squared
plus PY squared was conserved.
And in fact, that would be true.
Mhm.
You've gone through these with just a P
and a Q and
my sense I want to confirm is my sense
is
you're always talking about the same
index.
Well,
and
that for each index
Yeah. the transformation could be
different?
For each index, the transformation could
be different. Yes.
Yeah, yeah, but it's more complicated
than that.
Um
the transformation
No, there's one that Okay.
It's not that there's a transformation
for each index.
There's a set of transformations
Oh, there is a transformation for each
index. I take that back.
QI
is a function
not just of QI and PI, but of all the
Q's and P's.
Okay. So, there's a transformation for
each index, but each transformation in
general involves all the Q's and P's.
Yeah.
Right.
Yeah. What's What's the condition for
getting P if you know Q? Say it again.
What's the condition for getting P if
you know Q?
I remember what it was when we were back
in
the Lagrangian, but in this this form,
what is the
momentum that's
not the canonical with the Q?
How do you define
Oh, oh, how do you get the momentum in
terms of Q's?
Um
I think for this system, PY is actually
equal to X and PX is equal to minus Y.
Let's see. Can we see why that is? I'm
talking about the general
uh
I remember
P was
the uh
You mean how do we find the P's in terms
of the velocities?
Yeah, if you have a Q, how do you know
you know the
formula for the P that goes with it?
It's not always I think the I think the
The you're asking is how do you know the
P's in terms of the velocities?
Okay, yeah. I think that's the only
question I can think of that you could
ask.
always MV.
It's not always MV. No, but you go to
Hamilton's equations.
You go to Hamilton's equations and
Let's do it for an ordinary case and see
how it works for an ordinary case. We
could have H
is equal to P squared uh plus
plus some U of X, okay?
Let's just do it for them
Excuse me.
Let's just do it for the good old
familiar simple particle and we'll see
the pattern.
All right, so we just go to Hamilton's
equations. Hamilton's equations are
X dot
equals Poisson bracket
of X with with H.
And that's just going to give us P over
M.
That's it. That's it. That tells us P in
terms of X dot.
The other equation
is the equation that P dot
is equal to P with H.
And that gives us
uh
um
du by dx.
And that's of course F equals MA.
Force is equal to mass times
acceleration. So, one of the Hamilton
equations typically, the usual situation
is one of the Hamilton equations tells
you the relation between the P's and the
X dots
and the other is like Newton's
equations, involves the acceleration.
Yeah.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.